Finding aid to the Board of Counselors records CA.MS.00008
Smith College Archives
Board of Counselors records
1933-1998
Smith College Archives
Smith College. Board of Counselors.
CA.MS.00008
3.75 linear feet (9 containers)
Advisory committee to the Smith College Board of Trustees. Contains meeting minutes, memoranda, newspaper clippings and lists.
Biographical / Historical
The Board of Counselors was founded in 1950 by the Smith College Board of Trustees as an advisory committee. It was a revolving board made up of 25 members, originally either alumnae, their husbands, or fathers, who possessed some expertise and provided advice and opinions in specialized areas such as health, art, public relations, music, theatre, etc. Each counselor served on the board for five years, unless re-appointed. The Board of Counselors was divided into smaller committees which included: Afro-American Studies; Botanic Gardens; Campus School; Careers; Chapel; College Relations; Friends of the Library; Health Services; Multicultural Affairs; Museum; Nominating; Residence; School for Social Work; Science of Engineering; and Theatre. Each committee met once or twice a year. The Board of Trustees elected each committee chair and the general chair, who met annually in October at the time of the Trustees' meeting. The general chair of the Board of Counselors would then join the Board of Trustees meeting to report on the Board of Counselors' annual activity and advice.
Originally the Board of Counselors worked with the President of the College and the Board of Trustees in order to advise them in their duties of directing the college, as well as being available to the faculty for counsel and also worked with alumnae, friends of the college, and the general public to insure a wider understanding of college policies, plans, and needs. However, in 1998, the Board of Counselors stopped reporting to the Board of Trustees, and the position of general chair was discontinued. Instead, the committee chairs work more closely with department heads and senior staff members to serve the specific needs of each department. Committee chairs work with department heads to plan meetings as needed. The President makes all appointments to the Board of Counselors committees, including all committee chairs. Official committee correspondence, reports, and nominations for committee membership are channeled through the Office of the President. See the file titled History in Series I: General for an overview of the changes made to the counselors over the years.
Scope and Contents
The records of the Board of Counselors are composed primarily of meeting minutes, memoranda, newspaper clippings and lists. The documents were created between 1933-1998 with the majority falling within 1950-1988. There are a few photographs in Series I. General as well as in the files of individual counselors in Series III. Individuals. The records provide a good overview of the history of the counselors and the type of work they performed. The procedure manual dating from 1957-1971 is particularly useful for information about how the group organized itself and the purpose of the various committees.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into five series:
I. General
II. Subject Files
III. Individuals
IV. Annual Meeting
V. Committees
Additions to the Collection
Additions to these records arrive in the College Archives on a regular basis. Please contact the College Archives for the most up-to-date information.
Conditions Governing Access
The first three series: General, Subject Files and Individuals are open without restrictions. The series on Annual Meetings and Committees are permanently closed and open only to the Board of Trustees, the staff in the Office of the President, and the professional staff in the College Archives.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The records of the Board of Counselors came to the College Archives through various channels. Information about individual counselors and the activities of the group were collected by the staff in the archives over the years. In addition to that material, Rosemary Wilcox Dickerson '51, Chair of the Counselors from 1991-98, donated most of the annual meeting and committee materials (Accessions 98A-72, 00A-65). Material was also transferred from the Office of the President (Accession 00A-64).
Smith College. Board of Counselors.; Smith College--Administration.
- SERIES I. GENERAL, 1950-1998; 5 linear inches
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes historical information about the founding and operation of the Counselors. It also contains lists of the Counselors for nearly every year of their existence. Counselor lists can also be found in the Course Catalog. This series is open without restrictions.
  - By-Laws, 1950 (Box 267, Folder 1)
  - Chair Duties, 1950; 1990; undated (Box 267, Folder 2)
  - Committee Lists, 1955-58; 1968-74; 1984-87 (Box 267, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1950-1975 (Box 267, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1987-1991 (Box 267, Folder 5)
  - Counselor Lists, 1951-78; 1980-85; 1987-92; 1995; 1997-98 (Box 267, Folder 6)
  - History, 1950-86; 1998 (Box 267, Folder 7)
  - Mailings to Counselors, 1951-60 (Box 267, Folder 8)
  - Mission Statement, 1987-88 (Box 267, Folder 9)
  - News clippings, 1951-57 (Box 267, Folder 10)
  - Photographs, 1960-65; undated (Box 267, Folder 11)
  - Procedures Manual, 1957; 1966-71 (Box 267, Folder 12)
  - Publications, 1965; 1975; 1977; 1986; undated (Box 267, Folder 13)
  - Schedule, 1979 (Box 267, Folder 14)
- SERIES II. SUBJECT FILES, 1972-1991; 2 linear inches
  This series contains folders on subjects of concern to the college. Most of the topics center around the issue of diversity on campus. This series is open without restrictions.
  - Chapel, 1986-91 (Box 267.1, Folder 1)
  - Diversity, 1990-91 (Box 267.1, Folder 2)
  - Friends of the Library, 1972; 1982 (Box 267.1, Folder 3)
  - Lesbianism, 1991-92 (Box 267.1, Folder 4)
  - Multiculturalism, 1990-91 (Box 267.1, Folder 5)
  - Smith Design for Diversity, 1988-89 (Box 267.1, Folder 6)
- SERIES III. INDIVIDUALS, 1933-1976; 3 linear inches
  This series has a file for most of the individuals who served as counselors. The files consist of press releases announcing their election as a counselor and in some cases also a brief biographical sketch, curriculum vitae and/or a photograph. Lists of Counselors and their terms of service can be found in Series I, the College Archives card catalog under Counselors and in the Course Catalogs. These files are open without restrictions.
  - Abbot, Jere, 1933-35; 1941; 1967 (Box 267.1, Folder 7)
  - Anderson, Thomas D., 1962 (Box 267.1, Folder 8)
  - Arnstein, Robert L., 1960; 1965 (Box 267.1, Folder 9)
  - Averill, Janet White, 1966 (Box 267.1, Folder 10)
  - Baumgartner, Leona, 1972 (Box 267.1, Folder 11)
  - Bennet, Margaret Goldthwait, 1960-65 (Box 267.1, Folder 12)
  - Bloch, Jean Bowen, undated (Box 267.1, Folder 13)
  - Bodman, Herbert L., Jr., undated (Box 267.1, Folder 14)
  - Bornholdt, Laura, 1962 (Box 267.1, Folder 15)
  - Bradley, Wilson, Jr., undated (Box 267.1, Folder 16)
  - Byard, Margaret Mather, 1967 (Box 267.1, Folder 17)
  - Campbell, Marilyn Knapp, 1973 (Box 267.1, Folder 18)
  - Clark, Eleanor, 1974 (Box 267.1, Folder 19)
  - Comfort, Ethel, 1963-65 (Box 267.1, Folder 20)
  - deLaittre, John, undated (Box 267.1, Folder 21)
  - Deland, F. Stanton, Jr., 1967 (Box 267.1, Folder 22)
  - Dryfoos, Orvil E., 1962-63 (Box 267.1, Folder 23)
  - Fleming, Shirley, 1975 (Box 267.1, Folder 24)
  - Fulton, Joyce P., 1971 (Box 267.1, Folder 25)
  - Gamble, Ted R., 1950 (Box 267.1, Folder 26)
  - Gordon, Edward J., 1968-75 (Box 267.1, Folder 27)
  - Greenleaf, Cynthia, 1973 (Box 267.1, Folder 28)
  - Griswold, Mary, 1954; 1956 (Box 267.1, Folder 29)
  - Henneman, Esther Ogden, 1958 (Box 267.1, Folder 30)
  - Hirschberg, Nell, 1972 (Box 267.1, Folder 31)
  - Hofer, Philip, 1950 (Box 267.1, Folder 32)
  - Holden, John A., Jr., 1965 (Box 267.1, Folder 33)
  - Jakobson, Barbara, undated (Box 267.1, Folder 34)
  - Kelley, Peggy Clark, 1961-66 (Box 267.1, Folder 35)
  - Leab, Katharine Kyes, 1971-72 (Box 267.1, Folder 36)
  - Mason, Lucile, 1964-66; 1976 (Box 267.1, Folder 37)
  - May, Elizabeth Stoffregen, 1963-65 (Box 267.1, Folder 38)
  - Milliken, William G., 1967 (Box 267.1, Folder 39)
  - Morris, Frank E., 1972-76 (Box 267.1, Folder 40)
  - Niederman, James Corson, 1978 (Box 267.1, Folder 41)
  - O'Boyle, Nancy Millar, 1974 (Box 267.1, Folder 42)
  - Ostergaard, Ann, 1974 (Box 267.1, Folder 43)
  - Phelps, Edith Blakeslee, 1962-65 (Box 267.1, Folder 44)
  - Pitman, Helen S., 1965-66 (Box 267.1, Folder 45)
  - Pollack, Mabel Frown, 1963 (Box 267.1, Folder 46)
  - Powers, Frances C., 1962-63 (Box 267.1, Folder 47)
  - Rankin, Clara T., undated (Box 267.1, Folder 48)
  - Reynolds, George S., 1950 (Box 267.1, Folder 49)
  - Richmond, Eleanor Angle, 1965; 1968 (Box 267.1, Folder 50)
  - Robertson, Anne Tuck, 1976 (Box 267.1, Folder 51)
  - Scott, John Jay, 1968 (Box 267.1, Folder 52)
  - Smith, C. Cabanne, 1955 (Box 267.1, Folder 53)
  - Smith, Llewellyn P., 1970 (Box 267.1, Folder 54)
  - Sosland, Morton I., 1972-73 (Box 267.1, Folder 55)
  - Stair, Lois Harkrider, undated (Box 267.1, Folder 56)
  - Stookey, Elizabeth B., undated (Box 267.1, Folder 57)
  - Sutton, Percy E., undated (Box 267.1, Folder 58)
  - Tarlin, Janice, undated (Box 267.1, Folder 59)
  - Taylor, Nell Cochrane, undated (Box 267.1, Folder 60)
  - Thomas, Caroline Bedell, 1962 (Box 267.1, Folder 61)
  - Truman, Elinor, 1972 (Box 267.1, Folder 62)
  - Warburg, Frederick Marcus, 1954-58 (Box 267.1, Folder 63)
  - Weltman, Esther Ziskind, 1966; undated (Box 267.1, Folder 64)
  - White, Paul Dudley, 1950-55 (Box 267.1, Folder 65)
  - Wing, Virginia, 1964 (Box 267.1, Folder 66)
  - Wright, Moorhead, 1962 (Box 267.1, Folder 67)
- SERIES IV. ANNUAL MEETINGS, 1951-1997; 7.5 linear inches
  Conditions Governing Access
  RESTRICTED
  This series contains the agendas, minutes and supporting documentation for the counselors annual meetings. The files are permanently closed and open only to the Board of Trustees, President's Office staff and the professional staff in the College Archives.
  - Annual Meetings, 1951-53 (Box 267.2, Folder 1)
  - Annual Meetings, 1954-56 (Box 267.2, Folder 2)
  - Annual Meetings, 1957-63 (Box 267.2, Folder 3)
  - Annual Meetings, 1965-69 (Box 267.2, Folder 4)
  - Annual Meetings, 1970-74 (Box 267.2, Folder 5)
  - Annual Meetings, 1975-79 (Box 267.2, Folder 6)
  - Annual Meetings, 1980-85 (Box 267.2, Folder 7)
  - Annual Meetings, 1986 (Box 267.2, Folder 8)
  - Annual Meetings, 1987-90 (Box 267.2, Folder 9)
  - Annual Meetings, 1991-92 (Box 267.3, Folder 1)
  - Annual Meetings, 1993-94 (Box 267.3, Folder 2)
  - Annual Meetings, 1995-96 (Box 267.3, Folder 3)
  - Annual Meetings, 1997 (Box 267.3, Folder 4)
- SERIES V. COMMITTEES, 1950-1994; 2 linear feet
  This series includes the files documenting the work of the committees. The files include agendas, minutes and supporting documentation. The files are permanently closed and open only to the Board of Trustees, President's Office staff and the professional staff in the College Archives.
  - Afro-American Studies, 1968-70 (Box 267.3, Folder 5)
  - Afro-American Studies, 1971-74 (Box 267.3, Folder 6)
  - Afro-American Studies, 1975-88 (Box 267.3, Folder 7)
  - Afro-American Studies, 1989-91 (Box 267.3, Folder 8)
  - Afro-American Studies, misc. related materials, undated (Box 267.4, Folder 1)
  - Botanic Gardens, 1992 (Box 267.4, Folder 2)
  - Campus and Day School, 1971-75 (Box 267.4, Folder 3)
  - Campus School, 1976-88 (Box 267.4, Folder 4)
  - Campus School, 1988-91 (Box 267.4, Folder 5)
  - Campus School, 1992-94 (Box 267.4, Folder 6)
  - Careers, 1957-82 (Box 267.4, Folder 7)
  - Chapel, 1964-66 (Box 267.4, Folder 8)
  - Chapel, 1967-75 (Box 267.4, Folder 9)
  - Chapel, 1976-79 (Box 267.5, Folder 1)
  - Chapel, 1981-89 (Box 267.5, Folder 2)
  - Chapel, 1990-93 (Box 267.5, Folder 3)
  - College Relations, 1989-91 (Box 267.5, Folder 4)
  - College Relations, 1990-94 (Box 267.5, Folder 5)
  - Committee Recommendations, 1977-83 (Box 267.5, Folder 6)
  - Executive, 1969-70; 1974 (Box 267.5, Folder 7)
  - Friends of the Library, 1971-81 (Box 267.5, Folder 8)
  - Friends of the Library, 1982-87 (Box 267.5, Folder 9)
  - Friends of the Library, 1988-91 (Box 267.6, Folder 1)
  - Friends of the Library, 1992-94 (Box 267.6, Folder 2)
  - Health and Infirmary, 1950-75 (Box 267.6, Folder 3)
  - Health and Infirmary 75 YEAR RESTRICTION, 1959 (Box 267.6, Folder 4)
  - Health Services, 1977-91 (Box 267.6, Folder 5)
  - Infirmary, 1950-75 (Box 267.6, Folder 6)
  - Multicultural, 1992-93 (Box 267.6, Folder 7)
  - Multicultural, 1993-94 (Box 267.6, Folder 8)
  - Museum, 1971-88 (Box 267.6, Folder 9)
  - Museum, 1989-90 (Box 267.6, Folder 10)
  - Museum, 1990-93 (Box 267.7, Folder 1)
  - Museum, 1993-94 (Box 267.7, Folder 2)
  - Museum, 1995 (Box 267.7, Folder 3)
  - Museum, undated (Box 267.7, Folder 4)
  - Music, 1979; 1982; 1983 (Box 267.7, Folder 5)
  - Nominating, 1961-69 (Box 267.7, Folder 6)
  - Nominating - Candidates, 1954-55; 1970-80 (Box 267.7, Folder 7)
  - Nominating - Candidates, 1980-90 (Box 267.7, Folder 8)
  - Nominating - Candidates, 1990-93 (Box 267.7, Folder 9)
  - Nominating - Reports, 1955-70 (Box 267.7, Folder 10)
  - Physical Education, 1976-83 (Box 267.7, Folder 11)
  - Planning, 1957; 1971; 1975 (Box 267.8, Folder 1)
  - Program, 1957-58 (Box 267.8, Folder 2)
  - Public Relations, 1958 (Box 267.8, Folder 3)
  - Residence and Recreation, 1963 (Box 267.8, Folder 4)
  - Residence, 1975-80 (Box 267.8, Folder 5)
  - Residence, 1981-89 (Box 267.8, Folder 6)
  - Residence, 1991-93 (Box 267.8, Folder 7)
  - School for Social Work, 1976-92 (Box 267.8, Folder 8)
  - Science and Engineering, 1977-87 (Box 267.8, Folder 9)
  - Summer Internship, 1971; 1975 (Box 267.8, Folder 10)
  - Teaching and Research on Women, 1990 (Box 267.8, Folder 11)
  - Theatre, 1968-75 (Box 267.8, Folder 12)
  - Theatre, 1975-84 (Box 267.8, Folder 13)
  - Theatre, 1985-92 (Box 267.8, Folder 14)